[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
start recording and khalil i will
take you in hi
hi welcome back everyone um i'm khalil
from last time uh this is part two of
the sense maker in residence series
called
naturalizing sense making uh with dave
snowden
um we all know dave snowden for his
um his famous framework called
connection framework uh he's also the
founder and chief
scientific officer at cognitive edge
so for those who weren't here for for
the first part of this series
you can find it on the stoa youtube
channel
and how this is going to work is as
usual uh dave
i think he has something prepared about
the canvas framework
and then he's i'm going to hand it over
to him and we can post our questions in
the chat
if you have any questions post them in
the chat if you'd like me to read the
questions
um indicate that when you post questions
and uh without further ado i'll hand it
over to dave dave
okay i need to um check something
upfront how familiar are people with
the canadian framework i am i giving an
advanced presentation or am i giving a
introduction from scratch so if
if you're not familiar would you just
wave your hands around so i know how
many there are
okay right now because i'm going to do
what i want to try and get them today
and i may only do one of those
um is two basic sense making frameworks
um the one which is almost certainly
gonna get shifted to next
time unless i go really quickly is
called apex predator theory
which is a new context-based approach to
understanding when
you can change things and when you can't
change things
i there there isn't a universal on that
if i don't do it today i'll do it next
week
yeah um but i want to focus for the
moment on connecting and i want to do it
really in two sections one is a summary
of what canadian is about
but then i want to develop the new
material which is going to be published
shortly in the
european union handbook on how to manage
a crisis
which is actually specifically using
kinevin in the context of crisis
management
yeah and that actually has five separate
turns or processes you go through so
that's the basic idea um i know when i
share the screens i'm going to have to
use a picture and i can't draw which is
deeply frustrating i hate slides
but uh i know when i share the screen i
won't be able to see the chat
so i'm gonna try and sort of flip
between the two a little bit
um as we actually go on this
okay so i'll start off with general and
then i'll flip to slides
uh kinevin is a is a scientific
framework it's its origins
are in physics chemistry biology
um it's not a social construct you'll
remember from last time i talked about
the basic process we've gone through
which is to reject the idea of creating
frameworks from case studies
and instead take an approach which
interacts what we know from natural
science with practice
and uses natural science as a constraint
so what we actually see in nature is
three fundamental types of system
ordered systems complex systems and
chaotic systems
now i just want to be very clear now
this is an emerging field
people use language in different ways
yeah i i don't
i tend to get hung up on is it really
chaotic or do you mean random i'm going
to define my terms as i go
yeah and the basic definition i'm using
for this
comes from alicia gerardo and if you
haven't read the dynamics in action you
should read it
another new book coming out thank god at
last
next year i think yeah which is the
constraint based definition
so we have ordered systems complex
systems chaotic systems
they're defined by constraints so in an
ordered system the level of the
constraints
are so high that all behavior can be
determined
forecast and predicted so i've got a
high level of constraint i've got
predictability
i've got a linear material relationship
between cause and effect
and i'm using that in the aristotelian
sense of the word
that's actually very valuable it exists
in a lot of human systems
you know it is kind of like good news um
but then we get into the other types of
systems so undefined is a chaotic system
as one which has no material
relationship between cause and effect
or no effective relationship between
cause and effect
i there are no effective constraints in
play
which is kind of like a quasi-random
state everything is without connectivity
now what that actually means is it's
always a temporary state
um as axelrod famously said you know
order comes for free human
beings don't like chaos yeah
um it's kind of like you know somebody
would impose constraints pretty damn
fast or somebody will create constraints
and part of the problem with a chaotic
environment is you may not realize it's
chaos and somebody else may
impose the constraints and it's too late
for you to actually recover
so i'm using chaos in that sense of the
word other people will actually use it
differently
chaos is an unconstrained state or no
effective constraints
which means it's always a temporary
space it's not a permanent space
and then we get complete a complex space
and in a complex space
um everything is entangled
concept of entanglement is key
and everything is constrained in all
sorts of different ways
we we normally talk about enabling
constraints here
so the connections matter more than the
things something which i'll come back to
in the final lecture when i talk about
organizational change
um trying to change people actually
won't work and it's not ethical
yet trying to change how they connect on
the other hand is
more effective and i think can be
ethical right so
the connectivity is the key thing in a
complex adaptive system
and the whole point about the
entanglement and the connections is you
can't
fully know what they are you know the
bramble bush bushes in a thicket
metaphor from last time is key um
you know if i pull one bramble i don't
know what the impact will be
all sorts of things can can do that that
happens at the basic level i was
happily engaged in um dealing with wet
rot and dry rotting garden furniture
this afternoon which involves stringing
electrical cables the length of the
garden
and shall we just say there was a degree
of entanglement both with the electrical
cables and
also with my language all right as we
went through that process
so entanglement happens actually very
very quickly yeah
um so those are three basic types of
system
um and there are phase shifts between
them
uh and that's actually important to
understand if you want a metaphor in
this think about solid liquid and gas
and if you remember from high school you
remember latent heat
so you take water to 100 degrees it
doesn't become steam you have to put
more heat in
yet before it becomes steam and that's a
phase transition or a phase shift
kind of like the mathematics on this
backs me up and so no mark i don't see
it as a diode i see it as three distinct
systems
yeah um ordered systems complex systems
chaotic systems
there's an energy gradient between them
and that's really important to
understand so there's a hidden energy
cost of transition
and also it works the other way i mean
my children always laugh at me because
i'll come in in
you know february or march and say i can
smell snow coming
i grew up in the country i can smell
snow
they come we're losing a lot of skills
on this
right um the reason i can do that is
that in order for
liquid to become solid heat has to be
thrown out
so it always warms up a little bit
before snow comes
and that actually creates a sort of
olifactory stimulus which actually means
that if you grow up in your family and
you recognize it
you can sort of smell snow coming but
the point is
energy is given out or energy is
required
in the process of phase transition and
triggering a phase transition can
actually therefore release energy
as well as requiring it so that's the
kind like basic three
and you can actually draw kinevin as a
flat plane
brasso and i did this at the academy of
management years ago
in which the boundary between chaos and
order is shown as a catastrophic fold
now that's going back to renee tom yeah
so basically if you can imagine a flat
plane of paper and you fold the bottom
bit over so it looks like a wave
that's the boundary between order and
chaos and the danger is you don't notice
the cliff until you fall off it so
there's a basic principle here
yeah in terms of the phase transition
between order and chaos is a
catastrophic transition
in in the way it works right so yeah
it's the the straw that breaks the
camel's back and
and so on and so forth so if you have a
highly ordered system you're assuming
there's constraints and actually a
constraint is not sustainable
everything may seem perfectly normal to
you but then one day you wake up and
you've fallen off a cliff yet everything
has changed
so that that that's shown as a fold so
at its simplest level canaverin can be
shown
as a flat plane with a catastrophic fold
at the bottom
with those three types of systems
however
we move on from that because we're not
just concerned with the ontology of the
system
we're also concerned with the
epistemology and the phenomenology
yeah now in human beings that's quite
important because the three are separate
i mean they're obviously interlinked
what things are
how we know about things and how we
perceive things are three separate
separate aspects and by the way i'm
severely anti-social constructivism so
if we want to have an argument about
that later
that's fine you know kind of like
reality exists live with it is my
general response to that
um but the fact is that human perception
can differ from
human knowledge can differ from reality
and part of the use of kinevin is to
increase the friction between those
three i'll talk more about that in the
final election
if you can increase the friction between
the three you present the huge
misalignments which actually happen
i used to give the example of the
catholic church's misalignment with
science at the time of galileo
the more you miss a line when you have
to reset the reset is catastrophic
but there are probably better examples
in the uk and the us
at the moment i'm not quite sure who i
just like more
boris or trump but they're both trying
to out-compete each other
yeah in populist so there are other
examples so if you allow a system
to become over constrained you've got a
problem
so one links can having does is it
basically
divides and at this point i'm going to
go into share screen
um
i've got to find it now
okay so assuming everybody can see that
yeah um
that's actually the thing i talked about
last week that's the sort of sense
making diagram and the different types
and i can send the reference to the
paper
but coming back to kinevin can having
effectively has
five domains um
it doesn't have five quadrants i worry
about people who think they can be five
quadrants
it's rather like a former prime minister
in britain who said he wanted all
schools to be above average
yeah which rather showed that his wasn't
he even though it was eaten
so canarian had actually five domains
the chaotic and complex we've talked
about but what kinevin does
is it splits order into two
one where the relationship between cause
and effect is clear
and the other where it's complicated now
the division here is an important one
in the clear domain the relationship
between cause and effect is self-evident
everybody buys into it it's not disputed
yeah which means we can all do things
the same way the example i normally give
is that civilized countries drive on the
left-hand side of the road
whereas uncivilized countries drive on
the right-hand side of the road
you know kind of like it's a simple
bifurcation where am i
it's a classification system where am i
what type of
country is it which side of the road i
should drive and then go with it
sidebar on that by the way i mean before
kobe i used to drive around a lot
there's a whole issue about cognitive
entrainment and patterns if you hire a
car
in a right-hand drive country i can
drive without worrying about it
but if i take my car into france it's
actually dangerous
yeah that that sort of change of the
gear stick well yeah or whatever and the
steering wheel is key but that's the
sidebar
so that's kind of like where things are
clear um there's an
obvious relationship between cause and
effect in complicated it's different
the relationship between cause and
effect exists
but it's not self-evident it has to be
discovered it may be self-evident to an
expert
so you either have to trust the expert
or you have to do analysis or you have
to do research so what we then got is
clear
complicated complex chaotic
and then the central domain of canavium
which we're going to come to more at the
end of this presentation
which used to be called a disorder and
is now called confused
i mean to be honest this is a little bit
of marketing you know we've now got
five c's and it's complexity and it's
connecting there's lots of c so i can
add in coherence and
and lots of other words complexity has a
large sort of
number of c words so basically confused
means i don't know which of the systems
i'm in
and the danger with that is i will
actually assume
the system is the one i'm most
comfortable with
so if i'm a bureaucrat i'll assume that
the problem is a failure of process
if i'm an expert then you know it's just
simply
people didn't give me enough time or
money to investigate this properly
politicians are actually quite good at
the complex domain
um if they have a problem they can't
solve they just pull lots of people in
with lots of different ideas
and listen to them all which is actually
quite a good strategy
and of course fascists love a crisis
because then they can be given absolute
control to tell everybody else what to
do
in fact there's an old adage in this in
crisis management if you have a good
crisis manager fire them
because they probably created the crisis
in the first place because they enjoy
managing them too much
it's like if you don't know it the
majority of cases of arson
in bushfires are actually caused by
firefighters
now they actually like fires so if you
don't have enough naturally they'll kind
of like create them
so confused is about recognizing that
there's a state of not knowing which
system you're in
and as you say when we come to a crisis
to move things from chaotic to confused
makes a lot of sense okay you've got to
stabilize things quickly
so that allows us to actually look at
each domain now with a very different
perspective
so in the clear domain we can have best
practice
yeah the constraints are fixed there's
one right where i'm doing things if i'm
in america i drive on the right
if i'm in britain i drive on the left if
i'm in southern italy it doesn't matter
what side of the road i drive
um provided i flock it has actually been
studied and the way to drive south of
naples
is follow the next car match speed avoid
collision
yet if you do that it's a stress-free
driving experience if you try and follow
the rules it won't work
but in the majority of countries kind of
like it's a simple classification system
so i sense i categorize i respond
yeah that's kind of like the sequence in
the complicated domain on the other hand
um experts know but i have to actually
either trust the experts or do analysis
so i sense
analyze respond and now the constraints
aren't fixed and rigid they're called
governing constraints so they allow some
degrees of freedom
and and that's the important concept
yeah kind of like in the clear space
everything is tightly coupled
now the coupling is becoming looser
um so for example uh you know
you can get lots of differences so one
of the things you find if you work with
doctors which i do a fair amount
is that different surgeons will have
different views
uh when last december i was trey pan
which was an interesting experience
having two hulls
you know drilled into your skull it's
given me huge street cred with the new
age travelers around where i live at
avery but that's another matter
because it used to be associated with
shamanistic practice
but when the surgeon discharged me he
said oh
you had you he said it was interesting
the surgeon who was going to operate on
me wanted to put a
tube into the head to allow them to
check and drain later
but the surgeon who did operate me on me
didn't do that there were different
practices
and they have different reasons for
doing it in different practices around
that
and there's nothing wrong with that
because if you have the right expertise
you're allowed to vary the practice
and a big mistake people do is to try
and enforce best practice in a good
practice domain
okay so these that's what we mean the
difference between fixed constraints
there's one way of doing things
governing constraints provided you
satisfy the constraint condition you can
do things in different ways
best practice or good practice
um in the chaotic domain i'm going to
leave complexity for last
if you're in here accidentally as
opposed to deliberately we're going to
come on to the deliberate moves in a
minute
um then basically you've got to act
decisively to destroy the chaos you've
got to create some type of constraint
yeah there are no effective constraints
here it means that practice will always
be novel it's actually quite interesting
the old adage is there's nothing so good
as a crisis
to encourage innovation because what's
happened in a crisis
is the constraints have disappeared so a
lot of the in-train
patterns remember people don't see the
gorilla
yeah in the x-rays all of a sudden
people are seeing things differently so
you can get novelty
so the model there is accents respond
unless you go in there deliberately
now in the complex domain this is the
enabling constraints the way i normally
distinguish between governing
constraints and enabling constraints
is think about the difference between a
rule and a heuristic
yeah so a rule says thou shalt yeah
a heuristic says something similar but
it's different the best example i know
is the u.s
marines and i've done a lot of work done
at quantico
over the years and they have a simple
set of heuristics if the battlefield
plan breaks down
capture the high ground stay in touch
keep moving
now that's called an enabling constraint
it doesn't tell you what to do but
whether you've
complied with it is measurable
and i've done a lot of work with
companies from chanel
to south african mining companies to
identify the judgment heuristics which
are embedded in their normal stories
codify them and then distribute them as
a different control mechanism
because the whole point about a complex
world is you've got inherent ambiguity
yeah and you can't prescribe for
ambiguity in advance
one of the things we'll talk about later
on in this series
is the question about distributions and
remember i said this last week
in complexity we're in the tail of a
pareto distribution
not in the center of a normal
distribution
yeah which means the number of things
we've got to take into account is just
too high yeah and therefore we've got to
have some governing principles but we
can't pre-prescribe
what we should do and that's where
constraints come into play
vastly underused in management and also
generally in governance worldwide
but it's one of the important areas yeah
a lot of work on heuristics
uh especially linked with ritual and
practice here is x-active
now this is a phrase from biology if you
want a simple english phrase
as an alternative you can talk about
radical repurposing
all right so acceptation i'll give you
my favorite two biological examples
feathers evolved on dinosaurs for warmth
or sexual display
we've now got the evidence from the
discoveries in northern china
which actually say that all dinosaurs
had feathers of some type
yeah some got lots of feathers and those
are the dinosaurs that fell off cliffs
yeah or possibly ran at speed and took
off and glided
we can see those two pathways what then
happens is the feathers
which evolved which adapted in a linear
way
for one purpose and the conditions of
stress
except for something completely
different
now this was a key discovery in
evolutionary biology it's attributed to
gold and others
because until we had this there wasn't
enough time in human evolution
for the brain to develop the capacity it
has
but to give you my other example the
cerebellum at the base of your brain
which evolved in higher apes
to manipulate muscles in fingers accepts
in humans
to control grammar in language
so the huge sophistication of language
couldn't develop in a linear way it's
too big a leap
it required a non-linear extaptive
change
yeah now actually we now know that most
features of the human
of the human body happen accidentally
not by design
they evolve for one function then we can
like radically repurpose them for
something else
and we do this all the time anyway i
have radically repurposed
many things to open beer bottles in a
bar late at night in a hotel
without the proper instrument i'm
extremely good at that now i've got lots
of
models and then in 1945
a raytheon engineer maintaining the
magneto of a radar machine
notices that a chocolate bar melts in
his pocket
now he wasn't the first person to notice
this most people swore and got their
trousers cleaned
but he realizes the significance we get
microwave ovens
yeah the magneto is repurposed
thalidomide was developed in the
pharmaceutical industry for pain relief
it produced two side effects one was a
terrible one in deformed children
the other was the first ever cure for
leprosy
and that happened because people noticed
a side effect and of course farmer has
the most famous one of all
in that somebody wrote noticed a rather
unusual side effect in the drug
design for heart disease which have
resulted in viagra
so this ability well i call it small
noticings
the ability to notice something which
has new significance is key
to what we call acceptive innovation
rather than adaptive innovation in a
complex world
you've got every opportunity to
repurpose quickly
in order to get advantage and when i
talk about apex predator theory
i'm going to talk about the acceptive
moment the point at which you have to
repurpose
because you haven't got in time to
invent from scratch
if you want a good example of this
remember that ibm
repurposed their worldwide expertise in
punch cards
to get early dominance in computing
generally competitive advantage comes
the person who can repurpose existing
competence
for something new rather than the person
who invents from scratch
so acceptation is key then so that then
kind of like
starts to make the framework more
sophisticated
but then in a key
where's it
i'm trying to get the screen to change
but it stopped changing
until my best you guys but everything is
frozen
ah started to work now
this is a significant addition to knavin
it's one more line
um and i'll say now that my view of
sense making frameworks
is there is a basic test can you draw
them on the back of a table that came
from memory
if you can't do that they have no
utility yeah they kind of like
you know you see these big consultancy
models and dependency frameworks
and this came to me when i was in naples
with
my daughter looking at caravaggio's
paintings
and if you know his paintings you know
they
they use color and tone in quite
brilliant ways
and that was when i suddenly realized
what i've been looking for is the
anthropological concept of liminality
so liminality is a state of transition
or suspended transition
so if you go back to the original
anthropology when somebody puts on a
mask
yeah in in a ritual they go through a
liminal state of transition between
being who they were
and what the mask represents
now before we had liminality we had
dynamics and
arrows moving across canevin and we
actually found that people were very
confused by that they couldn't handle
two classification systems domains and
dynamics
by adding liminality we created the
concept of transition
yeah and that that was really important
because it changes the way people think
so it gives us actually four liminal
domains
one is the domain between complex and
complicated
so in the complex environment many
hypotheses
are equally valid i mean you've all been
there if you've been a decision maker
10 or 15 people come to you they've all
got perfectly coherent ideas you can't
decide who's right on the evidence base
yeah and you have to make a decision
that's actually a definition of a
complex environment
yeah if the evidence supports
conflicting hypotheses
and you can't resolve them on an
evidence basis within the time frame for
the decision making
it's complex it's a really simple way of
thinking about it
so instead of deciding what you actually
do is you run a safe to failed
experiment for each coherent hypotheses
and you run them in parallel not in
sequence
because you don't want no one want
what's called a hawthorn effect
anything novel always works the first
time for humans
it's a real problem with government
initiatives kind of like you know
a prototype will always produce good
results but it won't necessarily scale
comes from the hawthorne experiments
back in the 1920s
if you pay attention to people and do
something new
it will nearly always work
and that actually is a real danger for
people in terms of the way we do things
so basically in the complex world you do
multiple parallel
safe to fail experiments and the
experiments
change the dynamics of what's going on
so you can see what will work
if you've got it down to one or two
options then you move into the liminal
domain for anybody in agile
this is where things like techniques
like scrum come into play
you've now limited the hypotheses and
you just want to get the details right
you're going through iterative process
you're not yet firm
and you're trying to shift things into
complicated
because if you can shift things into
complicated you can scale at low cost
but there's quite high energy in doing
that because that's an upwards move on
the energy scale so that's that liminal
domain
between complex and complicated and of
course you may
then decide not to shift it over you may
want to keep your options open
the liminal domain with chaotic is
something i'll deal with next week in
more detail
that's where you actually deliberately
remove
all connectivity in order to allow for
novelty to emerge
it's kind of like an innovation space
yet you break existing constraints so
that the constraints no longer apply
we also use it for distributed decision
support this is the wisdom of crowds
concept
if i have a thousand people looking at a
situation
and interpreted it in parallel without
any connectivity i've actually got a
mathematical way
of making decisions under conditions of
uncertainty
yeah because if i remove all connections
i'm moving things to the center of a
normal distribution
whereas if i have connections things are
in the tales of a pareto distribution
i'll do more on that next week but the
thing the one i really love on wisdom of
crowds is a us submarine
which grounded off the coast coast of
portugal
it didn't sink i was corrected on that
by an admiral in norfolk navy base
he pointed out submarines are meant to
sink and i can't like learn from that
not to argue with a four-star you know
accept the ritual humiliation and get it
out of the way because then they'll
listen to you thereafter so it grounded
right they nobody knew where it was so
they gave
date the debt what data they had to
multiple groups of experts around the
world
including some nova scotia fishermen
because they know about the atlantic
yeah and all of them estimated where it
was
none of them were remotely right but a
probability distribution of all the
estimates was within 600 meters of the
actual submarine
all right now there are sound scientific
and statistical reasons for this
and a large part of our work in a crisis
is actually to move things into the
space
it's also how we find the seventeen
percent
the seventeen percent who've seen a
gorilla and can't understand why other
people haven't
going back to the first lecture okay now
the other two liminal domains i'm going
to deal with in a minute
um because they're within confused and
that's kind of probably going to finish
so this is why you'll see if you see
canva now you'll see it's marked as ac
so this central domain of confused is
actually a liminal domain
and confused now has two aspects being
confused and not being aware of it
actually puts you onto that catastrophic
fold it's a bad
place yeah the gray area is bad
the green however means you're aware
you're confused so you can do something
and we're calling that apparatic yeah
um it goes back to a whole philosophical
concept the whole rhetorical concept
um it's the concept of creating
paradoxes of ambiguity of unsolvable
problems so that you think differently
about things
so this is all about actually triggering
a series of changes
the creation of apparea
and i'm not really prepared to simplify
that one
so that leads me on to crisis management
and with this i'm going to
you know wind up and finish and open up
for questions
so in a real crisis you've got a i'm
going to talk about this in the context
of covid because this is where i've been
working for some time now
if you've got a major crisis the most
key thing you have to do
is to do a draconian imposition of
constraints to get you out of chaos
the new zealand prime minister did this
very well
yeah the us and the uk decided to wait
to see if they really had to do a
lockdown
she did a lockdown because it gave her
more options
yeah the whole point about draconian
constraint is to do things to give you
options
whether they're right or wrong yeah you
want to open up the option space
and that effectively is a shift into
operatic
the move you never do is to apply
existing best practice
that may well have got you there in the
first place
it's tempting and people will be arguing
for it but you shouldn't do it
so that's your first stage this is all
as i say about to be published in the eu
handbook on
how to manage in a crisis which i'm
writing
and we're jointly producing between the
canadian center and the european
commission
something which is rather ironic given
the stupidity of the english right we're
blaming them entirely for brexit
um there are then other moves
so the second move is a very simple one
um you'll probably find out that a whole
bunch of experts have been telling you
what was going to go wrong and you
haven't been listening to them
now there's nothing wrong with that if
you're a senior decision maker because
the number of people who are trying to
tell you what you're doing wrong is huge
in legion
and who you pay attention to is another
matter but now you can like know who you
should
so for example many governments haven't
been paying attention to epidemiologists
so if you have this problem you invite
the experts in you apologize humbly you
give them resource and you do what
you're told
that's one shift then a whole body of
problems will be long then
but you may also have this really
interesting area which is the liminal
domain
within complicated the one with the
question mark in it
that's where you've got experts who
can't agree
so we have that in britain with a
massive fight between epidemiologists
and behavioral economists
now that's where you have competing
expertise
and there's a whole body of techniques
we've developed i've blogged about one
of those today if anybody wants to read
up on it
called a triopticum which is a highly
ritualized encounter between three
experts with multiple participants
so it's ritualized it's short-term it's
not designed to have people lobbying you
it's designed to ritualize that process
of conflict
so you can decide where things go so
that's movement number three
we then get the other two moves movement
number four
is you kind of like have a whole series
of hypotheses about what you should do
and you think you've covered them all
off
right then you set up the safe to fail
experiments
small amounts of money to each different
idea we've been doing that with
actually developing a vaccine there are
many different approaches to that so
we're given different options here
if you're not sure that you know what
all the hypotheses are
then you move into that liminal domain
with chaos because you know
out there there are things or ideas the
that you need to pay attention to
now the key thing to decide on this is
do you go clockwise or anti-clockwise
yeah and the higher level of uncertainty
there's a trigger point where you go and
you go clockwise not anti-clockwise yet
you start
in that liminal domain with chaos but
that's going to create a lot more
uncertainty so you don't want to do it
unless you've got to
it's much easier to go anti-clockwise as
you move around that
so that basically is canaving
yeah um i just thought i'd show this so
you understand
some of the differences and also showing
the zimmerman framework and the stacy
framework
yeah they're based on human perception
right and actually balancing human
perception off kinevin is based on
actual ontology the nature of systems
it's a fundamental divide
and ralph and i have argued about that
from time to time
and barbara and i did when she was alive
yeah so you may see
other uses of the language but they're
actually different
okay that's one of my cats yeah that's
going to be an introduction to next
week's lecture um
that was when it was a kitten and the
first time it went out into the garden
that bird died shortly afterwards it's a
killer
so that will introduce apex predators
next week but that was kind of like a
summary of kinevin
a specific set of action at about
applications
um if you actually search for kinevin
you'll find it's being used i mean if
you on google scholar the the use is a
legion i published a brilliant little
video recently from a group in
um finland um who actually used it to
understand
deprived children in helsinki and lack
of social housing
um it's taught in you don't get to
command level in any of the american
military services without being taught
kinetic
all right so the whole thing is kind of
like just taken off in the ways that i
didn't expect one of things i'm proud
of is people can use it at different
levels it's fractal
people can look at it understand it and
use it without training but then they go
deeper and deeper and every time you go
deeper you find something else
and the reason for that is theory has
co-evolved with practice
it wasn't a one-time production
yeah as i talked with people the thing
developed and additional things get
added
it's probably a near finished state at
the moment
and i'm not sure we can do much more
with it and but i've said that before
and lived to regret it so i'm not making
a firm commitment
so that's a fundamental and another
phrase for this is multi-ontology
sense-making
one of the big drivers for canavin was i
got fed up of management fads
yeah so we do something which made a
difference and then it would stop making
a difference so we abandon it and start
again and i kept saying but it worked we
just
took it beyond its limitations there was
nothing wrong with business process
re-engineering
applied to core manufacturing but then
people tried to apply it to customer
service and it broke
so this is a concept called bounded
applicability
first work out the ontology and then the
epistemology follows
and actually one of the great things
about complexity if you're a philosopher
is it allows contradictory ontological
states to coexist
and that resolves a lot of problems in
philosophy but also a lot of problems in
business
it's a both and sense making framework
not a either or sense making framework
okay um i've done the 40 minutes and now
we've got 20 minutes for questions
and i'm open um
looking at the uh yeah thanks dave that
was that was great
this is also a gin and tonic just to
confess so
thank you dave that was that was great
um maybe i should just follow up with
one of my questions give
everyone a chance to put their questions
in the chat um
so yeah i never saw this this version of
ken evan with
the dimension of liminality in it and i
was wondering you talked a bit about the
evolution of
of the framework i'm wondering how this
specific aspect
how do you how do you come up with it
and um what was the
experience like uh realizing or coming
up with it
and i've just written 12 000 words on
the history of canavin which is
actually a complex metaphor with lord of
the rings
and and there's going to be a prize the
first person who can work out what i'm
referring to when i talk about
peter jackson's total corruption of
phalamia sorry
and that generation he destroys pharma
um and it was actually quite interesting
i was looking at the different things
which contributed to it and actually art
was significant and that was significant
in liminality
and remember i said last week one of the
functions of art in evolutionary history
is to allow abstraction so you make
novel connections
yeah so i had a problem which is people
didn't understand dynamics so we had
lots of different colored arrows moving
between domains and people didn't get
that
so they kept using it as a static
categorization framework
yeah they'd often draw it as a two by
two and put a token circle in the middle
to stop me attacking them
yeah and so on and so forth yeah though
i've been fairly tolerant over the years
and as i was you know in naples with my
daughter
um working with her on her anthropology
thesis so we had a father-daughter trip
to naples to study graffiti
if you want to study graffiti naples is
a great place the fact that we
coincidentally went to a few other
places like good restaurants and
herculean was
irrelevant right and father-daughter
trips were a lot of fun
um and we both loved caravaggio and we
were both
looking at the paintings in naples and
then that contrast of light and shade
yeah and the way in which
you know he also uses common people
to represent complex ideas of represent
the idea of grace
you know the whole point about those
paintings is that in a constant state of
transition
and that was what triggered the
liminality discussion
and if your daughter is an
anthropologist if you say is it liminal
then you then listen to a four-hour
lecture on liminality
yeah and then it all came from there so
that was actually how it came about
it was a problem which in the right
context had a solution presented
oh yeah that's excellent um
so yeah so i've seen some questions in
the in the chat so
uh i believe peter snowden had a
question about exactation of play peter
would you
like to ask your question
yeah sure no i mean it's just a very
small point but
um i remember reading um about
the role that play and non-proposal
activity played according to some um
archaeologists and anthropologists in
the development of for instance
tools for human use and
central function i'm just wondering how
that plays
with the more i don't know biological
zoological concepts of evolution
i i think it does i think you know play
i mean
art art and music come before language
in human evolution
yeah and that's significant and play
obviously those as well
i think what all of them allow us to do
is to separate ourselves
our set they they remove us from reality
so we can see it from a different
perspective
like that that's the value and although
it developed to something primitive it
then evolves with something very
sophisticated because of its utility
yeah it's why actually um
stem education is plain bloody dangerous
for the species
you know because we're focusing on stem
education and actually from a species
point of view particularly with climate
change and everything else we need some
more generalists and we need people
you know have that ability to play to
actually see things in art to see things
differently i get some of my best ideas
at the opera
yeah particularly wagner because wagner
is transcendental so you go to another
place all right
in in terms of the way it works
and we know that ritual is important for
humans
because ritual allows us to change we
work we view with the way we view the
world
so the plus side for human beings is
we've evolved
to various in very sophisticated ways to
separate ourselves from reality
the plus point is that makes us hugely
inventive the downside
is it makes us highly vulnerable to
conspiracy theories
and peter if you don't know we're
probably within three degrees of
separation
as relatives because that the name the
name
in both spelling comes from one small
village in northumberland and they only
left it about three generations ago
so you know that because
all snowden's are very closely related
we can't escape it
including the police chief of los
angeles but he was an ex-slavery name
so he doesn't count okay my family are
still close to the source then
because they're up on time side yeah oh
well there you are
all right that's interesting um
richard richards anita all right
thank you khalil dave it's an honor to
uh
to be able to speak with you directly
i've been following you for years
in defining confused early on which is a
beautiful new term
you spoke about moving from chaotic to
confused
and in my history of studying you you've
in the past spoken about moving from
chaotic directly to complex
and so my question is in is this a is
this part of something that you've
changed as you've moved as you've added
the concept of liminality to the model
yeah and i think it is always dangerous
on this i turned up at auckland
university once to give a lecture on
canadian
and discovered it was a masters class
all of whom were writing theses on
connectivity and thought
and it gave me all these references they
thought i'd read
and i was sitting there saying i haven't
read it i haven't read it honestly yeah
but um
yeah so that's the problem yeah i mean i
used to say there were two exits from
from chaos one was to move to complex
the other was to move to
what was then simple and the idea is
complex is safer because you can
experiment
we now actually have now changed that
and said it's better to move to confuse
yeah because that concept of our peria
gives you more options so yeah that is a
change
and i don't think i was wrong before but
i wasn't right
it's a very dave snowden specific answer
thank you dave yeah and he's having
hysterics in the background there i can
see him
[Laughter]
yeah so we have a lot of good questions
coming up dave are you able to save
a bit maybe a bit 15 minutes after the
hour
yeah no problem okay great and tonic has
got an inch left that's fine
perfect excellent so uh anjan i believe
you have the question
would you like to ask um
what are some popular books you
absolutely despise
as a book anything which says the seven
something or other or
you know anything like that yeah i mean
simplistic recipes
i'll tell you a story here i was mary
boone and i were having a phone call
um we're the book agent because we are
going to write the book
and i'm writing it with mary because it
was good writing the harvard article
with her
and she knows don tapstock and i don't
like don tabstock very much but she does
but either way he gave us a
book creation so we found that the book
agent go through the book plan
and he says no not interested and we
said why
he said too difficult too complicated
what i need from you is five books not
one book
and we said what do you mean and he said
you need to
understand the way this works what i
want is a book with a catchy title with
one idea with lots of cases
and i want one of those every 18 months
to two years
and we'll make our money on the speaker
fees and i thought
now i understand steve denning nicholas
taleb
all of these people that's what they're
caught into right
and the idea of creating something which
is a contribution to the field his
contract because he actually said that
he said no no no you
must claim originality it's got to be
completely new
and i mean that's the problem i got with
talib and anti-fragility i mean the idea
has been around for ages he didn't
bloody well invent it
yeah so i think those sort of simplistic
books are problematic
yeah and the other problem is the
confusion of correlation with causation
which is endemic
so you've got people who'll study ten
companies draw conclusions and think
they can trust in that and sorry my
background is in physics
no social scientist ever has enough data
to form any valid conclusion whatsoever
as far as i'm concerned uh and now
you've got the more recent ones i mean
it's like
um well one of the books i really
despise
is reinventing the organization by
francester crooks
because that's a guy who's got a
religious hypothesis
about how things should be and he only
selects
aspects of his cases to support the
hypothesis
and that's becoming increasingly common
yeah the
the use of partial aspects of cases
inadequate at the investigation to find
it
uh another one sorry you got me onto a
favorite subject and i'm in a polemical
mood at the moment
um another one is the concept of what's
it called um the book of acts
oh god it's a really popular one i
forgot the name of it
it's about startup companies so it
basically says you need to pivot and all
that sort of thing what's it called now
anybody remember lean startup
please yeah okay that's it all right now
i looked at that right this is a guy and
went who went to interview
friends of his who succeeded
now that's a really bad sampling
technique
and he identifies things they did in
common
and then says if you do these things you
will be successful
well i remember when i was in ibm's
research group
we did a project with dorothy leonard of
harvard who's a serious academic
and we studied companies which have
succeeded in companies who failed in
silicon valley
we actually study the ones who failed as
well as once succeeded
and we find they all did all the same
things there was no difference
yet the point is you had a market with
enough players that some are bound to
succeed
all right so those i often use in
lectures as examples
we have got a very trivial attitude to
book publishing at the moment
which is based on satisfying a need for
simplistic recipes
and easy answers and the problem as well
is our bloody politics is confounded by
that as well but
yeah thanks for that guidance uh we have
a question here with
two plus one so i'm going to ask it um
ask the person to ask a question
our beloved benito roy would you like to
ask your question
hi benita
you're on mute i mean i i wish i could
say i could do this anytime but you are
currently on mute
well done i love the new kinevin and
i've seen the uh
illustrations around but uh having you
present it was really cool
okay so this is kind of a a little bit
off topic
kind of hypothetical you know me um you
know
the subtext in a lot of this work is
that the world just gets more and more
and
more and more and more and more and more
more complex
and more chaotic maybe and i'm wondering
if you have a story
about the future in your mind where
there's some kind of bifurcation event
in which the ontology returns to simpler
best practice dynamics due to
you know some kind of integration of the
human mind or new realities
along the lines of you know people talk
about the release after the release
phase of anarchy do you see like just
the simple growing complexity or do you
see the the potential some kind of
catastrophic but advantageous
bifurcation event
they're not the extinction events after
which the cockroaches rule
right now this is somewhat
um yeah no not that
i i think there's a danger in this all
right in that i mean
and i say this as a as a good catholic
and somebody who's just starting a major
project to understand the numinous in
society
but there's a huge danger of us getting
mystical
about all of this stuff yeah
and assuming that somehow or other there
will be some major
phase shift and you can see this in two
ways you can see it
in the total nonsense of the idea that
we can put a human
brain into a computer yeah if
if you believe that it may be possible
for you because your brain is now
ossified to the point where it's it's
achievable
right um there's as much biology in this
is anything else i think the other one
is a sort of ken wilber integral
nonsense
and the concept of higher states of
being in transition between it
i mean the basic fact is we are
constantly evolving and changing and we
are losing and gaining capacity
um we could lose intelligence as well as
gain it
right and i actually think that the
problem at the moment
is connectivity and consequences not
complexity
so the world has always been complex but
the problem is it's now so
tightly connected and the consequences
of mistakes are so
high that we're at much higher risk
yeah um so
i'm not sure i'm answering the question
really but i wouldn't predicate action
on that as hope um terry eagleton
um if you haven't read terry eagleton
he's hugely prolific
there isn't a single book of his which
isn't worth reading
um his latest is called radical
sacrifice
yeah um but he's also
got one which is looking at hope yeah
and i can't i mean two seconds i'll get
it um
it's called hope hope without optimism
now that's i mean terry and i were both
editors of slant the catholic marxist
journal back in the 70s he comes from
that background
and both of us read milt moltmann if you
haven't read theology of hope that's
worth reading
yeah and i think one of the big things
we've got to start to introduce into
sense making is this concept of hope
without optimism because the danger is
if you have hope with optimism which is
the wilbur problem you end up
withdrawing from the world you've now
got the perfect
excuse to withdraw from action
so so that would be a but you and i have
talked about this
every now and then i was trying to find
the bloody scapula you gave me but i
can't find it now it's there somewhere
yeah it's an interesting hypothetical i
mean i i agree with you we have to live
in the world that we have and not
uh in the world that we think is coming
or some
hypothesized but yeah thank you this
notion of decoupling
uh loose loose coupled connectivity but
looser coupling i know you've talked
about it that i think is
the move we're looking for the other
thing which is worth reading at the
moment is this one
yeah because that that's kind of like
going beyond the anthracene
um and david david is really good on the
anthracene as well so that there are
some serious academic texts on looking
at this
concept theological shift uh stephanie
wakefield also
i there's a group of what i call post
anthropic thinkers
that are i would say that they're able
to really
uh be patient in the limbo
spaces that you're talking about and you
get to do sound talk i mean remember i
spent a lot of the 70s in kakadu
in northern australia yeah working
with indigenous communities and that was
hugely educational actually a lot of the
techniques like ritual descent came from
that
what's fascinating indigenous
communities is all this bloody nonsense
about everybody being nice to each other
doesn't apply
yeah it's kind of like you know the
reality of
neolithic lifestyle requires something a
little bit more sensible than that
if you haven't seen it tan canoes is a
brilliant film as well
yeah and jan caporta was on the store
and he was talking about
people torturing each other or something
or you know kind of giving that flavor
of tribal society punishing that's what
he was saying
anyway thank you very much
that was a great exchange of the i would
love to hear dave talk about
uh these religious topics more sometime
with hope and sacrifice
um well yeah we have a question by dan
feldman dan would you like to ask your
question
uh yeah sure let's can you can you copy
it down in the bottom again
for me i believe it was
um it's nice just nice to talk to you
dave i've been uh reading your stuff for
quite a while
um my question is what
is uh a multi-ontology
sense-making way to translate what is
typically called the problem and
solution in the ordered space
how would you translate problem and
solution into the other
into the other domains that language i
guess
i may or may not have understood the
question but let me try some answers all
right
one of the ways that we work i mean
first of all
and we'll do this next week when i do
apex predator theory
complexity is taking off at the moment
i remember when systems thinking went
from academic idea to dominant
concept and took about three to four
years
yeah so it's actually very fast when it
happens it's a phase shift it's not a
gradual shift and we're seeing that with
complexity
which worries some of us because the
wrong type of complexity you think it
could come out on top
yeah and and that's why i and others
make quite rigid distinctions between
systems thinking and complexity thinking
because we don't want confusion between
the two
now we can go into that later yeah so
one of the ways that
certainly i've introduced it over the
years is to find intractable problems
don't go for the low hanging fruit
yeah governments and industry and the
higher up you get the more they get
complexity
you don't get to be on the board of a
major international company without
understanding that there's a lot of
stuff you can never know
and i mean one of the other frameworks i
developed back in 1980 was an
uncertainty matrix which compared
known unknowns and then nobles
right um and that was an ontology
epistemology framing
and i remember presenting that in the
pentagon once a few years ago at the
request of john poindexter and after
that i couldn't use it again for about
four or five years because it got
tainted
yeah but yeah i still use that with
executives so if you've got
unknowable unknowns
you can't apply conventional wisdom
the other one which is really scary for
executives is
unknown gnomes so that's where people in
your organization know what to do but
you don't know that they know it
yeah so you start to focus them on those
and then they're prepared to use
complexity methods
right the other thing is tools are
important i mean one of the reasons we
developed sensemaker apart from it being
counterterrorism
was the ability to demonstrate something
like if we do this you can see this look
at that picture what you think
it means is that's one of the other ways
you make it tangible for people
now i may not have answered the question
you asked i answered the question i
heard
so that's always a danger well it's just
i
i guess it's the use of the word
solution a lot of people you know they
define
whatever the problem is whether it's a
complicated problem or usually it's a if
it's a social problem
uh most of the time it's in the complex
space for my assessment
and it tends to be this is the problem
that has multiple complex untangled
roots and here's our solution and
somehow that is that that
that i cringe when i hear that there are
parts of it that you can do i mean
there are three basic principles of
complexity management all right so one
is
optimize the granularity of what you're
dealing with
which generally means smaller things the
other is
distribute and diversify cognition
and the third is disintermediate
decision makers
if you follow those three you can't go
far wrong and people keep talking about
a system as being complex or complicated
when actually aspects of it are complex
and aspects of it are complicated
so one of the things kinevin is designed
to do is to find the things which aren't
complex which you know what to do about
and also to find the things in the
complex domain and i can
do this next week if people remind me
because one of the key things we do with
executives is constraint mapping
because constraints are ordered aspects
of a complex system
so one of the ways you can change things
is to change the constraints
okay excellent
peter limberg your question had a
oneplus so i'm going to let you ask your
question
cool all right so
the question is uh any good examples
current or past of political and or
social movements consciously imposing
states of liminality between the
ontological domains
in order to enact change interest and uh
temporary autonomous owned by the that
anarchist
hakeem bay comes to mind uh
yeah you you shouldn't talk to a former
catholic marxist leninist
about our anarchists you know we
we kind of have two methods to deal with
them one involves pickaxes and the other
involves altered the phase
right um and anarchism always gives way
to fascism by the way
um i think there are liminal states i
mean you could argue the mensheviks were
a liminal state
in the russian revolution i'm thinking
aloud here
right um i don't think
i think the problem with anarchism is
it's too informed by
libertarian concepts of identity
so it over focuses on the individual and
when we talk about this last time the
difference between social atomism and
communitarianism
and um i think if you get
communitarianism you get the fact that
our identities are collective not
individual
then there are multiple states of
liminality that could exist
right um we're doing some work at the
moment which if anybody's interested in
happy to talk to more people about on
the whole issue about
citizen juries and citizen assemblies
and we're looking at ways and we're
doing some of this with extinction
rebellion
which hopes uh the deciding which quite
fancy is the
uk prime minister making me a terrorist
again i've always wanted to be a
terrorist
um sorry the uk prime minister is
planning to ban
ban climate change activists as
terrorists it's ridiculous right
so we're doing some work with them at
the moment on um
actually using mass engagement to inform
citizen assemblies
because one of the things we've got to
start doing is rethinking democracy
because democracy wasn't designed to
work with populations of the size we've
got
with the long-term consequences of
a short-term decision focus all right so
the current political system is not only
broken
it's potentially going to kill us
right so that's one of the areas we're
working and that
is actually about creating liminality of
decisions to allow new
new solutions to emerge right now that's
something which doesn't happen
in a two-party state or a one-person
one-vote state
where people are effectively yeah
abbreviating their ideas it doesn't work
either if you delegate your ideas
electronically that's a cute idea but
that won't work either
so i think one of the things where a lot
of us are trying to do
is to create more liminality
yeah because liminality keeps options
open for longer
that's great um we're kind of running
out of time so maybe we can have
one or two more questions we'll see um
jeff
jeff irving would you like to ask a
question
oh hi um yeah thanks um
i won't try to reread what i what i
wrote
what was on my mind was whether if you
could speak
to how people's uh
default preference of how they see
themselves
operating within a preferred domain so
uh hi i'm jeff
i think of myself as particularly suited
to
making sense of the world from the
complex domain interferes with
how i could effectively leverage kinevin
i think i mean two things on this side i
don't want to go down a myers-briggs
route
um i mean that that's one of the worst
pseudo-sciences around at the moment
and people who put their myers-briggs
scores on their business card
need therapy fast in my view right
um reality is most of us are capable of
operating in all domains very quickly in
fact we always do it i mean the one
i mean the children's party story which
you can look up online
which is the best teaching story i've
ever created
yeah fundamentally makes the point that
we manage our children on the assumption
that a complex adaptive system so we
know how to do it
yeah in terms of the way where we do
things so all of that's available
we do to have done some interesting
projects one things i did in singapore
and singapore funded a lot of the
experimentation on this
is we actually created the canadian
framework with
six ministries and they worked in cross
ministry teams so we created it
with lots of exemplar narratives to
define the domains and the boundary
spaces
and we sent them away for two weeks and
we brought them back and put them into
ministry teams
and we gave them all of the exemplars
but without the way they were positioned
and asked them to create the canadian
framework for it
and they created six completely
different versions even though they all
worked together before
yeah so what you actually found is the
foreign office but everything every
everything was simple or
clear because they just wrote reports
after the event
ministry defense i was quite proud of
but there again i was an advisor and
i've been training them for five years
they could they kept near the same
distribution
yeah and the home office put everything
into complicated if you think about it
well they're evidence-based they're
police
yeah so that was fascinating because
we then put the we created the charts
and said well we see it like this you
see it like that there's nothing wrong
with that
but we need to realize there's a
miscommunication there
yeah and that's something called
descriptive self-awareness one things we
do a lot i mean
the famous case on this is a sense maker
one where we were working on the
um aroma problem within europe
so we got roma kids to act as
ethnographers to roma people in hungary
and they got access to data nobody has
ever got before
yeah no external research would get that
and then we took clusters of narrative
which has been indexed the same way by
roma people
and we gave it to the european union
anthropologists in vienna and said
interpret this the way you think roma
interpreted it
and then we showed them the difference
and the difference was huge
this happens a lot all right and there
are three responses to this
one response is to say oh my god we
should see it the same way they do and
that's just ridiculous
yeah you can't do it you're an expert
you can't see things the same way unless
you're gerard calls this a gradient
there's a difference between you
the difference is actually quite
creative if you accept it
yeah um so the right one is to say that
right
the really bad one is what we got from
the anthropologists in vienna is they
don't understand their own stories we're
the experts we understand what they
really mean
and that is ever so common in what we
call distributed ethnography
the expert can't cope with being shown
the difference so
a lot of the work you do around
complexity
is to constantly throw people into
positions where they can't
challenge the process right
if you come in as an expert they can
challenge your expertise or they can
challenge the process
if you take them through a process and
they can't challenge it and they can see
that as a result of the process they saw
it like this and you saw it like that
then you have a chance to change and
that's one of the ways kinevin is used
in practice
so yeah i think i'm afraid we have to
end there i apologize
to everyone else who had questions uh
this is
part two of four so there'll be two more
um sessions with dave in this series
uh that was rich and engaging as usual
dave thanks again
and i'm just going to pass it over to
peter to close up the session
great uh thank you dave um any any kind
of um
advanced preview for uh next week what
we're going to talk about
next week i'm going to look at apex
predator theory
um and the issue about when can you
change things
and when can't you change things in the
nature of change
very cool uh so i'll send you this uh
i'll post this up probably today
uh or tomorrow and you can um you can
actually download the chat
directly right now i believe if not i
will send it to you via email again
uh upcoming events at the stowa
uh tonight we have joe norman uh talking
about applied complexity
that's at eight pm eastern time and uh
we have a series of sense makers and
residents here
peter wang is one of them and he's going
to talk about the mental models he uses
to navigate all the complexity
of this world and that's tomorrow
10 a.m eastern time and anita roy has a
sense maker in residence series
coming in october uh benita can i uh
take you and put you on the spot and you
maybe can plug it a bit
yeah so it's called the hollow um
so it resonates with halloween and a
hollow
is like a riverine a kind of landscape
where people used to meet
uh to conspire to
throw over the government and it also
resonates with dogen's notion
of hollow bones and hollow bone zen
it's a little bit of a
yeah it's a i think that um
it'll be interesting uh series
thank you benita and you can recipe on
the the website the stove.ca
sign up for the mailing list and if you
like these events and want more of these
events
you can support us on the patreon that's
that's uh the stoa
patreon so yeah thank you david thank
you everyone for coming today see you
next week